什么  你刚才  说什么
What? What did you-What?
我仍然爱着你
I still love you.
我知道我甚至不该来这里告诉你
And I know I probably shouldn't even be here telling you this.
你跟钱德在一起  我很喜欢他
I mean you're with Chandler, a guy I really like.
你说他是异性恋   我就相信你
and if you say he's straight, I'll believe you.
但见到你之后  我知道我不说  会后悔一辈子的
After seeing you the other night I knew if I didn't tell you I'd always regret it for the rest of my life.
放弃你是我所做过最蠢的事
Letting you go was the stupidest thing I ever did.
你不该到厨房来的
Y’know you're really not supposed to be back here.
对不起  我知道时机地点都不对  但是
Well yeah, I'm sorry. I know this is the wrong time and the wrong place but...
我一定要说
...I had to tell you.
我想跟你共度一生  我想娶你
I want to spend my life with you and marry you.
我想跟你生儿育女
I want to have kids with you.
哇  天哪
Oh, my God.
这里为什么没摆椅子
Why don't they put chairs back here?
我知道这很疯狂  来不及了吗
I know this is crazy, but am I too late?
没错  来不及了  这些话你3年前怎么不说
Yes, you're too late. Where was all this three years ago?
我知道  我是个白痴
Well I know. I was an idiot.
我也想忘记你  真的
And I tried to forget you. I really did.
我们去年吃完饭  我跑到非洲待了6个月想忘记你
Y'know after  we had lunch last year, I spent six months in Africa trying to get you out of my head!
你去非洲做什么  帮助盲童
What were you doing in Africa? Working with blind kids.
你折磨我啊
What are you doing to me?
怎么说呢
Look,L...
很抱歉  我们之间是不可能的了
I'm sorry, but umm, this-this is not going to happen.
也好   我会离开的   再也不会来烦你
That's fine. I'll walk away. And I'll never bother you again.
但唯一前提是  你要告诉我  钱德也愿意给你这一切
but only if you tell me Chandler's willing to give you everything I am.
他愿意  没错
Well, he is. Yeah, I mean...
他整天把婚姻挂在嘴边
...marriage is all he talks about.
老天
My goodness.
事实上  是我在让他等
In fact, I'm the one making him wait.
是吗   对啊
You are? Yeah.
为什么  为什么
Why? Why?
因为政府的阴谋
Because of the government.
老友记  第六季  第25集  求婚（下集）
Friends  S06E25  The One With The Proposal
主演: 珍妮佛·安妮斯顿
主演: 寇妮·考克斯
主演: 丽莎·库卓
主演: 麦特·勒布兰
主演: 马修·派瑞
主演: 大卫·修蒙
很棒吧
Isn't it incredible?
摩妮卡和钱德要结婚了
Monica and Chandler are getting married.
就是啊  他们会很幸福的
I know. They'll be so happy together.
两个最要好的朋友坠入爱河   这种机率有多大
I mean two best friends falling in love. How often does that happen?
并不太大  没错
Not that often. No.
我好替他们开心啊
I'm so happy for them.
我也是  好开心
Me too. So happy for them.
我很高兴  毫无嫉妒之心
I'm so happy and not at all jealous.
没错  没错   当然没有了
Oh, no! God, definitely not jealous. Mm-mm.
我可能是98%的开心  2%的嫉妒
I'm probably 98 percent happy and maybe 2 percent jealous.
2%  等于没有
What's 2 percent? That's nothing.
没错
Totally.
我是9比1  我也是
I'm like 90-10. Yeah. Me too.
你们看见钱德了吗
Hey, have you guys seen Chandler?
没有  但你知道谁来找过你吗
No. But you know who did stop in here looking for you?
坦妮尔
Tennme.
（约翰披萨店）
关于婚姻   你昨天说的那些话
So that marriage stuff you were saying yesterday?
应该不是真心话吧   当然是
You don't really believe that do you? Sure, I do.
事实上  我觉得婚姻本身就很不近人情
In fact, I think the whole concept of marriage is unnatural.
你看猪嘛   我们来看一下猪
I mean look at pigs. Let's take a second here and look at pigs.
猪不会有固定配偶
Pigs don't mate for life.
猪的一生可以有一百个性伴侣
I mean a pig can have 100 sexual partners in a lifetime.
那还只是普通的猪  而不是擅长运动的猪
And that's just an ordinary pig, not even a pig that's good at sports.
等一下
Wait a minute.
你是说  你可能永远都不想结婚
Are you telling me you may never want to get married?
话不能说死  不过应该是
Well, never say never, but y'know, probably...
永远不会
yeah, neven
天哪
Oh, my God.
那我们在干什么   现在又是什么啊
Then what are we even doing?  What is this?
哇哇哇  干嘛对我施压
Whoa, whoa, whoa, what is all this pressure?
这是某种新策略吗
Is this some new strategy?
你别再搞尔虞我诈那一套了
Why don't you put down your copy of The Rules, huh, man-trap?
你知道吗  我要走了
You know what? I gotta go.
放心  我自有打算
It's okay. I got a plan.
我们会找到真爱的   一定会的
We're gonna find love. Definitely.
我对这一点有信心
Yeah, I'm pretty confident about that.
所以我可以有八成   替摩妮卡和钱德高兴
That's what makes it so easy to be 80 percent happy for Monica and Chandler.
不过要是有保障就好了  什么意思
It would be nice to have a little guarantee though. What do you mean?
有些人会跟朋友约定
Well, some people make deals with a friend.
要是两个人到了40都还单身   他们就结婚
Like if neither of them are married by the time they're 40, they marry each other.
你是指备胎   没错
You mean a backup? Exactly.
我已经找好了
Yeah, yeah. I've got that.
你找好了
You do? Mm-hm.
是谁   乔伊
Who? Joey?
乔伊  真的  对
Joey? Are you serious? Yeah.
真的  我好几年前就锁定他了
Yeah, I locked him in years ago.
所以要是你们40岁都还单身   你就嫁给乔伊
Wait. So if neither of you are married by by the time you're 40, you'll marry Joey?
对  我们握手为定
Yep. We shook on it.
不过相信我  他可不一定这么想
Yeah. But believe me, that is not how he wanted to seal the deal.
是吗
Seriously?
对  他说的是
Ohh, yeah. I think his exact words were...
真迷人
Charming.
他只是个备胎
Ah, he's just a backup. Yeah.
摩妮卡
Hey, Monica.
你有见到瑞秋  或是镜子吗
Have you seen Rachel? Or a mirror?
这是我的船长装   酷吧
This is for my boat. Cool, huh?
很酷
Yeah, it's great.
怎么了  告诉船长吧
Whoa-whoa, What's the matter? Talk to the captain.
我发现这段感情又是死路一条
I'm just having one of those days where you realize you're in a dead-end relationship!
钱德欺负你是吧
Chandler's giving you a hard time?
我又不是明天就要结婚   我只是想知道
It’s not like I want to get married tomorrow. It's just that I-I'd like to believe...
我是不是在原地打转   浪费我的时间
...that I'm in a relationship that's actually going somewhere, that I'm not just wasting my time!
你也了解钱德  不  我已经不了解钱德了
You know Chandler. No, I don't know Chandler.
完全不了解了  就像发生了什么事情了
Not anymore. It's like something's changed.
也许是你变了
Maybe you changed.
我才没变
I didn't change.
也许问题就在这里
Maybe that's the problem.
什么   钱德是很复杂
What? Chandler is a complex fellow.
不太可能娶个妻子
One who is unlikely to take a wife.
他在想什么  他以为我会空等下去吗
What does he think? Does he think I'll just gonna wait around for nothing?
面对现实吧   钱德反对婚姻
Monica face it. Chandler is against marriage.
他是不会变了
And always will be.
有些人可是真心想娶我
Well, there's some people who do want to marry me.
有吗   谁啊   理查
There are? Yeah. Richard.
理查说他想娶你
Richard said he wants to marry you?
而钱德说他讨厌婚姻   没错
And Chandler says he hates marriage? That's right.
钱德热爱婚姻
Chandler loves marriage!
你刚才说他讨厌婚姻
You just told me he hates marriage!
他很复杂  不太可能娶妻
That he's a complex fellow who's unlikely to take a wife!
而且他反对婚姻   一直都没变
That he's against marriage and always will be!
你这样理解我的话
You got that from what I said?
瑞秋  嘿  帅哥
Rach. Hey, you.
嘿  请进  谢谢
Hey, come on in. Thank you.
你跟伊丽莎白分手了  真可惜
Hey y'know, I'm so sorry to hear about you and Elizabeth.
谢谢  我以为我们会白头偕老
Oh, thanks. Yeah, I really thought we'd be able to make it work. but uh,
结果却是有缘无份
I guess it just wasn't meant to be.
是啊  爱情
Yeah. Love.
爱情真是微妙   对吧
It's a tricky business, isn't it?
是啊
I guess so.
那我们要不要来做个约定
So, what do you say we make a pact?
要是我们到了40还都单身   我们就结婚
If you and I are both single by the time we're 40, we get married.
我们双方熟知   而且喜欢对方
I mean, we know each other, we like each other...
还上过床   彼此不会感到陌生
...we've already slept together, so y'know there'll be no surprises there.
你知道我意思  不会觉得  "大惊小怪"
You know what I mean? No, like, "What's that?"
懂了  你是想找我当备胎   没错
Oh, you want me to be your backup. Exactly.
可是我已经有一个了
Oh, yeah. I already have one.
什么  谁啊  菲比
What? Who? Phoebe.
菲比
Phoebe?
但是她说乔伊是她的备胎
Wait a—but-but she just, she said that Joey is her backup.
哦  才不是呢
Oh, I don't think so.
罗斯   我刚跟她聊过   她说她和乔伊约好了
Ross! I just had a conversation with her. and she said that she and Joey made a deal.
不可能的   我们几年前早就约好了
That's impossible. I mean we have had a deal for years.
还握手为定
We shook on it.
只不过她觉得握手还不够
Although, believe me, she wanted to do a lot more than that.
你跑到哪儿去了
Where have you been?
我在跟教授做椰子电话
I was making a coconut phone with the Professor.
理查跟摩妮卡说  他想娶她
Richard told Monica he wants to marry her.
什么  就是啊  我一直在找你
What? Yeah! Yeah, I've been trying to find  you.
叫你别再跟她玩了
to tell to stop messing with her!
可是这双船鞋跑一跑就掉
And maybe I would have if these damn boat shoes wouldn't keep flying off!
天啊   就是啊   这双鞋好恶心
Oh, my God! I know! They suck!
他不该向我的女朋友求婚   该求婚的人是我
He's not supposed to ask my girlfriend to marry him! I am supposed to do that!
我知道  那
I know! What--?
看我怎么教训他  我要去找他  狠狠揍他一顿
You know what I'll do? I'll go over there and kick his ass!
你会帮我吗
Will you help me?
钱德  我们海扁他一顿也不是解决办法
Look, Chandler I don’t think us getting our asses kicked is not a solution.
知道吗
Okay?
赶快去找摩妮卡吧   你说的对
Look, just go and find Monica. You're right.
我去拿戒指  去拿戒指
Okay. I'm gonna get the ring. I'm gonna get the ring!
我要找到她
...I'm gonna go find her ...
直接向她求婚
...and I'm just going to propose!
老兄  老兄  老兄
Dude! Dude! Dude!
你的椰子电话  也许很适合摆在船上
Let me know about that coconut phone might be good for the boat.
嘿
Hi.
我不知道我来干什么
I don't know why I'm here.
我又没问
I didn't ask.
要进来吗
You want to come in?
不知道
I don't know.
好吧
Oh, okay.
那我把门开着  然后坐到沙发上
Well, I'll just leave the door open and go sit on the couch.
钱德真是个笨蛋
Chandler is such an idiot!
喝点什么
Drink?
威士忌加冰块和莱姆片
Yeah, I'll have a scotch ... on the-Rocks with a twist?
我记得
I remember.
还在抽雪茄
You still smoking cigars? Uh...
不  没有  那只是"烟雾的艺术"
No, no. That's art.
如果你不喜欢   我可以把"艺术"灭掉
If it bothers you, I can put my art out.
没关系
No, that's okay.
那么  摩妮卡
So, Monica...
我问你一个问题
...let me ask you a question.
我们分手后  你有没有
Y'know, since we broke up, do you ever...
想过我
...think about me?
几个月前还想到过你
Actually, I thought about you a couple months ago.
真的吗   不过是因为
Really? Yeah, but it's because I...
我去做眼科检查   而我又不喜欢我的新医生
...had an eye exam, and I don't like my new eye doctor.
谁   爱德华奈夫斯基
Who is it? Edward Nevsky.
没错  他是不怎么样
Yeah, he's no good.
不检查眼科的时候
Do you ever think about me in...
你有想过我吗
...a non-eye-doctor way?
没有
No.
啊
Ah.
忘记你是我这一生最难的事
Because getting over you was the hardest thing I've ever had to do.
我努力  不让自己想到你
I never let myself think about you.
菲比   你霸占了乔伊和罗斯
Phoebe, you picked Joey and Ross?
你不能有两个备胎
You can't have two backups!
当然可以
Of course I can.
眼光独到才会替备胎找备胎
It's just good sense to back up your backup.
我已经失去了钱德   什么
Look, I've already lost Chandler. What?
喂   菲比
Hey, Phoebe!
我们俩都是你的备胎
We're both your backups?
菲比  你怎么可以这样对我
Phoebe, How could you do this to me?
我不知道你们在抱怨什么  你们都很清楚
I don't—Look I don't know what are you complaining about now? You were both aware of the situation.
不  我们不清楚   我也不
I was not! No, we weren't!
看来婚后我们还要这样不停地顶嘴
Okay, this kind of back talk isn't gonna fly when we're married.
菲比  你不能两个都要  只能挑一个
Phoebe! You can't have both of them! You have to pick one!
选我   不   选我
Pick me! No, pick me!
我不想当老处女
I don't want to end up an old maid.
好吧  我看看
All right well, let's see.
罗斯是个好爸爸
Ross is a good father.
但是
But...
乔伊有条游艇   好难选啊
...Joey has a boat. This is hard.
太过分了   我要改换瑞秋
This is crazy. Hey look, I want to switch to Rachel.
我也改换瑞秋
Ooh, I wanna switch to Rachel too!
不   等一下   等一下
No, wait! Okay, just wait!
等下  伙计们  别急着做决定
Wait, guys. Wait you guys! Don't make any rash decisions.okay?
记得我的承诺吧
Just remember my promise:
结婚之后  1星期3次
If we get married, three times a week.
天哪  菲比
Oh, my God. Phoebe...
我是说按摩
I'm talking about massages.
不  我不是说按摩
No, I'm not.
我知道该怎么解决了  这样就是了
Okay, y'know what? I know how to settle this. All right here, Here's what we'll do.
我在一张纸巾上
I'm gonna write "Joey"...
写 "乔伊"
...on one napkin.
另一张纸巾上写 "罗斯"
And I'm going to write "Ross" on the other napkin...
然后我们一人选一张
...and we are going to pick one!
抓到谁  谁就是我们的备胎
And that person will be our backup.Okay? Here we go.
很公平   那好
That sounds fair. All right.
好  我先弄乱
Good. Switching them up.
挑一张  左边的
Pick one. Left.
谢谢  不客气
Thank you. You're welcome.
罗斯  乔伊
Ross. Joey.
我们交换好了   没错
We should just switch. Absolutely.
我想念这套公寓
I miss this apartment.
这才是成年人住的地方
Now, this is a grownup's apartment.
我要跟大人在一起  你明白吗   明白
I should be with a grownup, do you know what I mean?! Yeah.
你是说  你要跟更成熟的人在一起
You're saying you need to be with someone more mature.
也许是一个
Maybe someone with...
有医师执照的人
...a license to practice medicine.
或是留胡子的人
Or a mustache.
说真的  我不是小孩子了
Let's face it. I'm not a kid anymore.
我需要和一个目标相同的人走到一起
I need to be with someone who-who wants the same things that I do!
来我上班的地方向我示爱   就是我要的
I mean coming to my work and telling me you love me, I want that!
吃饭时闲扯猪的性爱   那样的我不要
Talking about pig sex over lunch, I don't want that!
我认为很公平
I think that's fair.
公平  别跟我提公平
Fair? Please. Don't even talk to me about fair.
公平的意思是  当年你想娶我
Fair would've been you wanting to marry me then.
或是钱德现在想娶我  都没错
Or Chandler wanting to marry me now.
真的  整件事一点也不公平  一点也不
Believe me, nothing about this is fair. Nothing.
不公平   不公平   别激动
Nothing! Nothing! It's okay.
嘿
Hey. Shh.
不公平
Nothing.
不知道
I don't know.
我不知道
我知道
I know.
好了  我
Yeah, I-I...
我得先把事情
I have to figure...
想清楚  然后才能
...some stuff, before I can...
我懂
Yeah, I understand.
你只管慢慢想
Take as much time as you want.
10分钟  20分钟都行
Ten, 2O minutes, if you need it.
我会在这里  不抽烟
I'll be here. Not smoking.
钱德   她人呢
Chandler. Where is she?
我才不怕你
I'm not scared of you.
她不在  请进
She's not here. And please come in.
威士忌加冰
Scotch on the rocks...
和莱姆片  放在杯垫上
...with a twist, on a coaster.
摩妮卡  摩妮卡
Monica? Monica?
好吧   她来过了  又走了
Okay, she was here. But she left.
去哪里了
Where did she go?
她说  她要去想清楚
She said she had to think things over.
天哪  我真不敢相信  我还以为你是个好人
Oh, my God. I can't believe this. I thought you were a good guy.
我们又没怎么样
Oh, hey. Look, nothing happened.
没怎么样  没怎么样  你没跟我女朋友示爱
Nothing happened? Nothing? So you didn't tell my girlfriend that you love her?
好吧  我说了
Well, all right, one thing happened.
你知道你在做什么吗
Y'know I can't believe this! Do you know what you did?
搞得我女朋友在这东想西想的
My girlfriend is out there thinking things over.
你竟然让我的女朋友想这些事情
You made my girlfriend think!
我很抱歉
Well, I'm sorry.
她有什么好想的   我爱她
And what does she have to think about? I love her.
显然  她想要的我能给她  你却不能
Well, apparently I'm willing to offer her things that you are not.
但是我也愿意给她那些   我只是计划着
I'm willing to offer her those things. This was just a plan.
先故意让她失望   然后让她喜出望外
y'know? A way to throw her off so when I offered all these things, she'd be surprised.
她的确很意外  这效果确实很好
Well if it helps, it worked very well.
本来一切进展顺利   你却半路杀出
It was working till you showed up, you big tree.
这不公平
This isn't fair.
你有过机会  结果却搞砸了
You had your chance with her, You had your chance and you blew it!
现在轮到我了  我不会放过的
And this is my chance and I won't blow it...
因为我们是天生的一对
...because we are meant for each other.
现在不过犯了个愚蠢的错误而已
And this has all just been one stupid mistake!
我本来打算今晚求婚的
I was gonna propose tonight.
你要求婚
You were gonna propose?
对  我还
Yeah, I even...
准备了戒指
...got a ring.
你准备了戒指
Did you get a ring?
没有  我没准备
No, I don't have a ring.
你能得到她的  钱德
You go get her Chandler.
不过  我能给你一个忠告吗
And can I give you a piece of advice?
要是你能得到她
If you do get her...
一定要好好珍惜
...don't let her go.
相信我
Trust me.
理查  你的确是个好人
You know, Richard, you are a good guy.
这我知道
I know.
我恨这点
I hate that.
钱德  待会儿再说  我得去找摩妮卡
Dude. I can't talk to you now,  I've gotta find Monica.
她走了
She's gone.
什么  她走了  提着个包包走了
What? She’s gone. She had a bag and she left.
你说什么  她哭得很伤心
What are you talking about? She was all crying.
说你们追求的目标不一样   她需要时间思考
She said you guys want different things and she needs time to think.
你为什么不栏住她   告诉她这只是个计划
Well why didn't you stop her?  Why didn't you tell her it was a plan?
我说了  我都说了  钱德   但是她不信
I did! I told her everything. Chandler! She wouldn't believe me.
那她  去
Well, where--?
她去哪儿了
Where did she go?
她父母家吧   我想  她叫你不要打电话找她
To her parents' I think and she said you shouldn't call her.
要是我就会打
But if I were you, I would.
这事我居然搞砸了
Can't believe I ruined this.
我很遗憾  伙计
I am so sorry, man.
你希望给她个惊喜的
You wanted it to be a surprise.
天哪
Oh, my God.
钱德
Chandler...
我这辈子
...in all my life...
从来没想过我会这么幸运
...I never thought I would be so lucky...
可以爱上我最要好的
...as to fall in love with my best...
我最要好的
My best...
所以女孩子从不主动求婚嘛  好吧  好吧  好吧
There's a reason why girls don't do this! Okay, okay, okay.
我来  我曾以为
I'll do it. I thought...
等等   我来求婚吧
Wait, I can do this.
我以为  开口求婚的
I thought that it mattered...
时间地点很重要
...what I said or where I said it.
后来我才发现
Then I realized...
唯一重要的就是你
...the only thing that matters is that you...
你让我得到超乎想像的幸福
You make me happier than I ever thought I could be.
所以如果你愿意
And if you let me...
我愿意付出余生   让你跟我一样幸福
...I will spend the rest of my life trying to make you feel the same way.
摩妮卡
Monica...
你愿意嫁给我吗
...will you marry me?
我愿意
Yes.
我就知道你会娶妻的
I knew you were likely to take a wife!
可以进去了吗   我们等得快急死了
Can we come in yet? We're dying out here!
进来吧   进来吧
Come in! Come in!
我们订婚了
We're engaged!
噢
Oh!
这是我最不嫉妒的时候
This is the least jealous I've ever been!
等等  不行  罗斯不在场
Oh, no, wait! This is wrong! Ross isn't here!
哦
Oh. Oh.
算了吧   他都玩三次了   知道这是怎么回事
Oh hell, he's done this three times. He knows what it's about!
没错
Yeah.
Oh, my darling
You were wonderful tonight